<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Verblog</title>
  
  
  <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2023-12-26T21:27:29.861Z</updated>
  <id>http://verbey.github.io/blog/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Verbey</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Studying Japanese</title>
    <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/12/26/studying-japanese/"/>
    <id>http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/12/26/studying-japanese/</id>
    <published>2023-12-25T22:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-12-26T21:27:29.861Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“OMG, dude, are you a weeb or something?”</p><p><img src="https://media1.tenor.com/m/9UbaYJIP_XAAAAAd/jojo.gif" alt="Mohammed Abdul from JoJo&#39;s Bizarre Adventure saying &quot;Yes! I am!&quot;"></p><h2 id="How-did-I-get-into-studying-Japanese"><a href="#How-did-I-get-into-studying-Japanese" class="headerlink" title="How did I get into studying Japanese"></a>How did I get into studying Japanese</h2><p>こんにちは! So, this was the situation half a year ago:</p><p>The university made us choose 2 additional subjects from around 30. Most of them were useless, like business planning, which was one of the two subjects that I chose (you know, the type of subject where you will be told that you are poor because you have the wrong way of thinking). </p><p>Among one of them, a few language subjects stood out: Italian, Chinese and Japanese.</p><p>I know my university had cultural exchanges with people from the respective countries, so I knew I would learn at least <em>something</em> there.</p><p>But I could only choose one, so I had to make my choice wisely. </p><p><em>Italian language</em> was taught at the <em>computer science</em> institute, so it was the first one to go as an option. By the way, before you ask the question, I will tell you the answer: “I don’t know why. What I do know, though, is that study at a very cursed place.”</p><p>Chinese is a very popular language, for obvious reasons. Why learn Japanese when there will be more uses for Chinese?</p><p>Well, because I have been told a story that my university has some good Japanese teachers. In particular, I’ve heard that one of the professors here lived for some time on the Kuril Islands, where he was taught Japanese by native speakers.</p><p>I don’t know if any of this is true because it was passed on to me as gossip, but the old man does have a Japanese state award and even has a Wikipedia article about himself. No ordinary person can have that.</p><p>Also, I happened to have been exposed to Japanese media. This influenced my decision as well. Just a little. I promise.</p><p>Considering this, I have made the decision to study Japanese.</p><p>Also, I happen to have been exposed to Japanese media. This influenced my decision, too. Just a little. I promise.</p><p>Considering this, I made the decision to go with studying Japanese.</p><h2 id="First-impression"><a href="#First-impression" class="headerlink" title="First impression"></a>First impression</h2><p>It’s crazy. Being a European, naturally, I find it hard.</p><p>The hardest thing, in my opinion, is <a href="https://www.japan-guide.com/e/e2046.html">Kanji</a>. For those who don’t know, Japanese has 3 writing systems: Hiragana, Katakana, and Kanji. Despite all of them being based on the Chinese hieroglyphs, the kanas only have symbols for representing a fairly limited set of sounds.</p><p>Kanji (translated as Chinese letters), on the other hand, consists of thousands of hyeroglyphs, which could even have <a href="https://www.kanshudo.com/howto/how-to-read-kanji">different readings</a>. Scary, isn’t it? </p><p>Also, when a European person begins learning the language, they are immediately struck with massive cultural differences.</p><p>Showing your respect is very important. Doing so is a thing in all cultures, I think, but the Japanese will be going an extre mile with that one.</p><p>Also, when learning about modern Japan you can’t help but run into <a href="https://www.businessinsider.nl/what-is-karoshi-japanese-word-for-death-by-overwork-2017-10?international=true&r=US">the culture of overworking</a>. </p><p>Wealth of Japan, its national capital, is the product of an immense sacrifice of its workers. Billions of working hours put to the altar by millions of workers.</p><h2 id="Lessons"><a href="#Lessons" class="headerlink" title="Lessons"></a>Lessons</h2><p>In our lessons, we use an online textbook as our main resource.</p><p><a href="https://marugotoweb.jp/">Marugoto</a> is an excellent all-in-one resource. Our teacher only works as a mentor, answers advanced questions, helps with pronunciation etc.</p><p>This is actually very good because it makes studying more or less self-paced. If you want to, you can rush and go through all the topics in a week. If you missed some concept you can always revisit it later.</p><p>Tasks in the A1 section are dead simple and repetitive, yet it’s all you need at this point of learning — get a grasp on some of the most basic communication. More understanding as to why the language works the way it does will come later.</p><h2 id="Exam"><a href="#Exam" class="headerlink" title="Exam"></a>Exam</h2><p>Have you ever had your mark be lowered because of JoJo? No?</p><p>What a <em>bizarre</em> question, right? Well, I did.</p><p>For the exam, we had to do a test on the Marugoto platform and write a short text about ourselves.</p><p>So… I thought it would be a good idea to start the text with an edited version of the <a href="https://www.twitchquotes.com/copypastas/3451">Kira Yoshikage copypasta</a>.</p><p><img src="https://media1.tenor.com/m/WUI9r_HPt6EAAAAd/my-name-is-kira-yoshikage.gif" alt="Kira Yoshikage saying the lines of the copypasta"></p><p>Well, as it turned out, the teacher (せんせい, <em>sensei</em>), made us read aloud the first two sentences and judged the final grade on them, whilst ignoring the rest of the text. That was most unfortunate because the two sentences that the text started with, were the pasta, written without due <em>respect</em> one should’ve shown in a more formal environment.</p><p>Long story short: JoJo ruins people’s lives. And grades.</p><p>Thankfully, I still got a good grade - 80%. I would have lost my mind if Japanese was <a href="/blog/2023/12/17/update-on-how-things-are-going/">yet another subject</a> for which I had to work my ass off to get a pitiful grade.</p><h2 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion"></a>Conclusion</h2><p>Japanese is an interesting language and I genuinely like it despite the fact of how hard it is. I might not have as much free time nowadays as I used to in the past, but it gives me joy to spend it on studying it.</p><p>I might not be well-versed in it and can only understand some basic phrases, but look forward to reaching new heights and feel very proud of myself each time I can spot something in Japanese in the wild and read or translate it.</p><p>Oh, I almost forgot that one. Setting up the input for Japanese on KDE Plasma sucks. One R*ddit commenter suggested this might be the reason the Japanese don’t use Linux much.  </p><p>As a cherry on the top of the post, I would like to offer you this hot take: hiragana looks better than katakana.</p><h2 id="Bonus-Useful-resources-for-self-studying"><a href="#Bonus-Useful-resources-for-self-studying" class="headerlink" title="Bonus: Useful resources for self-studying"></a>Bonus: Useful resources for self-studying</h2><p>These are the resources I stumbled upon during my studies and highly recommend to anybody who would like to learn the language as well:</p><p><a href="https://marugotoweb.jp/">Marugoto</a> - self-paced free course for basic Japanese.<br><a href="https://f-droid.org/en/packages/com.LAPARCELA.nihonoari/">Nihonoari</a> - useful app for studying Hiragana and Katakana. With that one, I memorised most of the characters from both alphabets in a matter of days!<br><a href="https://ohelo.github.io/usagi-chan/">Usagi-chan’s hiragana and katakana challenges</a> - another useful resources for memorising the kana.<br><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/LearnJapanese/wiki/index/">r&#x2F;learnjapanese’s wiki</a> - good meta resource for finding other resources. Unfortunately, hosted on Reddit.<br><a href="https://www.tofugu.com/">Tofugu</a> - a neat blog with articles answering questions you might have and some good visuals.</p><hr><p>Written with love by verbey, edited with a free plan by our future overlord - <a href="https://editgpt.app/">artificial intelligence</a>.<br>Thanks for reading to the end of the post, otsukaresama desu! :D </p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“OMG, dude, are you a weeb or something?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media1.tenor.com/m/9UbaYJIP_XAAAAAd/jojo.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Mohammed Abdul from</summary>
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="japanese" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/japanese/"/>
    
    <category term="languages" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/languages/"/>
    
    <category term="uni" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/uni/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Update on how things are going</title>
    <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/12/17/update-on-how-things-are-going/"/>
    <id>http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/12/17/update-on-how-things-are-going/</id>
    <published>2023-12-16T22:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-12-16T22:57:48.778Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="A-little-preamble"><a href="#A-little-preamble" class="headerlink" title="A little preamble"></a>A little preamble</h2><p>When I published my last post, <a href="/blog/2023/11/08/useless-work/">Useless work</a>, I couldn’t even imagine it would only go downhill from there.</p><p>Now, let’s talk about why I haven’t posted anything in more than a month.</p><h2 id="Computer-Logic-Coursework"><a href="#Computer-Logic-Coursework" class="headerlink" title="Computer Logic Coursework"></a>Computer Logic Coursework</h2><p>Seriously, when you hear you will have to write 100+ pages of a coursework by hand, you think it can’t get any better than this.</p><p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/HG7B5P1/handwriting-coursework.jpg" alt="Willy Wonka meme asking in patronising attitude whether you think handwriting coursework is awful"></p><p>At the very least, the subject for which I had to do that turned out to work by the “carrot and stick” formula. For my immeasurable suffering and sleepless nights, I was offered a 95% score on the subject and a 90% score on the coursework itself. </p><p>If you hand in the coursework before the deadline, which is not that hard, to be honest, then you are able to have the exam held online. Totally worth the hassle.</p><p>Oh, and I also discovered how much hatred I can have for 159 A4 pages of paper — <em>a lot</em>.</p><h2 id="Computer-Electronics"><a href="#Computer-Electronics" class="headerlink" title="Computer Electronics"></a>Computer Electronics</h2><p>Do you know what is <em>not</em> worth the hassle, though? Computer electronics assignments!</p><p>The assignments are dead simple: replicate a scheme in Multisim, make some screenshots. Then calculate some formulas and compare the obtained data to that on the screenshots. It’s quite simple, despite taking a lot of time.</p><p>Too bad, the old fart checking the assignment doesn’t want your life to be simple.</p><p>To actually get a grade for the assignment, you must go through a circle of hell called “Захист роботи” (literally translated as “Defense of the assignment”, I can’t think of a proper alternative in English at the moment). You must answer a bunch of question from the professor, which are <em>slightly SIGNIFICANTLY</em> harder to answer than whatever you were preparing for.</p><p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/s34H6KW/class-homework-exam.jpg" alt="Meme about homework assignments that are always harder than classwork, and exam questions being the hardest"></p><blockquote><p>Oh, so you were doing what for this work? What? I can’t hear you, sorry. Anyway, here’s a scheme I just made up in my head, calculate the voltage at its exit. Ah, wrong answer, 0&#x2F;5 mark is what you deserve.</p></blockquote><p>The whole group has low grades now, because we weren’t lucky enough to get a teacher who wouldn’t sabotage us with his cool questions aimed at computer geniuses.</p><p>By the way, we had to write the theory for the assignments by hand. Digitalisation didn’t go well in this place, as I can see.</p><h2 id="Other-subjects"><a href="#Other-subjects" class="headerlink" title="Other subjects"></a>Other subjects</h2><p>Less interesting, but those still gave me enough pain in the ass.</p><p>Mostly because of how nice were the deadlines. Our assignments would be checked on week X, yet the lector thought it would be a good idea to put a deadline for uploading them to Moodle on week X-1.</p><blockquote><p>These students must have such a lot of time, gotta make them work hard for once in their life.<br>– Every professor ever, probably.</p></blockquote><p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/dJGY48X/5tg8wd.jpg"></p><h2 id="What’s-planned-next-for-the-blog"><a href="#What’s-planned-next-for-the-blog" class="headerlink" title="What’s planned next for the blog"></a>What’s planned next for the blog</h2><p>In between the suffering I’ve had different things happen and read some articles and played some games and coded some scripts etc. and all of that is <em>blog-post-idea-provoking</em>. Some posts are almost finished, for some I had only written down the titles.</p><p>Now that the semester has ended, I can dedicate time to the blog, which will make me and, hopefully, you happy.</p><p>I was also planning to get this place a nice domain, so you wouldn’t have to see the ugly GH Pages URL each time you go here.</p><p>May there be no misery in your life, reader.<br>Signing off,<br>Verbey</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;A-little-preamble&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#A-little-preamble&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;A little preamble&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A little preamble&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I pub</summary>
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="meta" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/meta/"/>
    
    <category term="personal" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/personal/"/>
    
    <category term="uni" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/uni/"/>
    
    <category term="studying" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/studying/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Useless work</title>
    <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/11/08/useless-work/"/>
    <id>http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/11/08/useless-work/</id>
    <published>2023-11-08T10:40:02.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-08T19:39:36.301Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you ever feel like you are doing useless work? You might have heard of the term “bullshit jobs”. The way we are taught at my university could be called “bullshit studying.”</p><p>Here, our time is not spent wisely. I would often find myself doing questionable tasks because professors couldn’t come up with something better.</p><p>Take, for example, <a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/math/multivariable-calculus/integrating-multivariable-functions/triple-integrals-topic/a/triple-integrals">triple integrals</a>. I have no idea when I would actually need to use those in computer engineering. People in this country don’t make hardware parts themselves anymore. Nowadays, the technology is much more advanced, and the volumes of details you are going to use will already have been measured with the result provided to you.</p><p>Though I, at the very least, have a very clear understanding where triple integrals are used. There may come a time when I will be required to calculate the volume of a particular item, and I will possess the necessary knowledge to accomplish this task.</p><p>The whole other story is when you don’t even know how it can be applied! We spent over 80 hours studying series. Some of that was dedicated to solving problems where we had to determine if the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alternating_series">alternating series</a> were conditionally or absolutely convergent.</p><p>One small question: WHY?! There are many more examples of the theory we learned, but that doesn’t give much explanation as to why we were learning it. This type of material could have been provided as additional information or only be mentioned in lectures, so we know it <em>exists</em> but don’t waste our precious time on it and do something interesting instead.</p><p>It is common for students to rant about concepts they don’t exactly understand. People in my group were often critiquing discrete math as a subject, although it had very useful stuff in it like <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/earth-and-planetary-sciences/graph-theory">graph theory</a>, and I sometimes argued with them that there are ways you can actually put it to <a href="https://www.javatpoint.com/graph-theory-applications">good use</a>.</p><p>However, I just can’t stand assignments that have handwriting as a requirement or ones with useless or outdated information. It’s just a waste of <em>everyone’s</em> time and effort.</p><p>We would be fed outdated material that would cost the professor nothing to update. It is one thing when they can’t tell us something because they don’t have access to the most modern computers, machines, or expensive subscriptions to scientific journals, but it is completely another if it was only told to us because the professor couldn’t care less about teaching something good.</p><p>Like that one time when we were learning programming and our lecturer unironically suggested using Hungarian notation for naming our variables in C++. For how long has Hungarian notation been a thing of the past? A decade? Or even two?</p><p>Now, what about writing coursework by hand? Yes, in 2023, somewhere in Eastern Europe, students will still write hundreds of A4 pages by hand <em>every year</em> for university.</p><p>Why is this a thing? What insane mind thought it would be a good idea? I don’t know. I don’t want to know. I just want to not spend my time doing that.</p><p>Also, since COVID-19, students have had to submit their tasks online in a digital form, be it a <code>.pdf</code> file or a <code>.docx</code> one. Now that we are not quarantined anymore, we are once again required to print out reports.</p><p>What a waste of Earth’s resources! For most subjects, we have to submit digital versions of the documents <em>too</em>. If you have the digital version, then why require a printed one? It doesn’t make any sense.</p><p>There are even some professors and lecturers who actually try to be “good”, use modern technologies, etc., and they cringe so hard whenever I tell them I write coursework for this subject by hand. Nobody thinks this is normal in 2023, except for some sadistic farts.</p><p>It doesn’t have to be like that, the learning process can be made good with some effort.</p><p>I do have some sympathy for the lecturers, however. One of the reasons they are who they are is because they are not paid enough to actually care.</p><p>The role of a personality is undeniable, but there is an extent to which personal actions influence the world, there are boundaries and effects caused by socioeconomic relations in the human community.</p><p>People are formed in society, you can’t live <em>in</em> it and be free <em>from</em> it. If the society is not willing to compensate for the proper teaching and the ones you teach are incentivised to ignore their studies in favour of a job, even if it is not related to their speciality and does not pay much, then this is what you get.</p><p>All of this makes me alienated from my own work. What I do doesn’t belong to me; I never wanted to do that; I wanted to study something else, in another way. I look at over 70 pages of my coursework, and I can’t feel anything but depression.</p><p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/vB7r6xRF/932e64a1a2450b6fe42b2663c4815d5e.gif" alt="An animated image of an anime character being exhausted from doing paperwork. Very relatable"></p><p>&#x2F;rant</p><p>Stay safe out there, and may you be blessed with enjoyable and actually meaningful learning in university.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you ever feel like you are doing useless work? You might have heard of the term “bullshit jobs”. The way we are taught at my universit</summary>
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="personal" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/personal/"/>
    
    <category term="uni" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/uni/"/>
    
    <category term="studying" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/studying/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Just do it. A motivational post</title>
    <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/10/21/just-do-it/"/>
    <id>http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/10/21/just-do-it/</id>
    <published>2023-10-21T13:20:30.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-10-21T13:00:40.614Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One thing that I noticed about people that excel in some field is that they use the time when they’re bored to do something related to the said field.</p><p>When they have free time instead of lying around being bored, browsing social media feed they would solve Math problems, program, do language exercises etc.</p><p>They are good at something because they do it. They do it because they like it. That’s why they do it <em>regulary</em>. </p><p>This part is often overlooked. People want to excel at something overnight, except it never works like that. You can’t get big muscles unless you exercise regulary, you can’t get a Ph D for reading about a subject for a whole day non-stop.</p><p>It is all a matter of dedication over a long period of time. Even if you don’t like doing it, you will finish it faster and better through doing smaller bits.</p><p>That thing that you want to do but keep reappointing to a latter date, do you <em>really</em> think you can get grasp of it without starting now?</p><p>You can do it and you know it, but you procrastinate because you don’t know what to do, until the moment comes and you feel brave enough to wander into the field for an extended period of time without having the slightest idea of what you are doing.</p><p>As always, quantity forms quality, so to “conquer” the quality of something hard and unknown you have to divide-and-conquer your way, which best works when doing it on set intervals of time.</p><p>Stop the procrastionation. I believe in you. </p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Some motivation for those who might need it..</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="personal" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/personal/"/>
    
    <category term="motivation" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/motivation/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>My thoughts on the Odin Project</title>
    <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/10/07/odin-project-thoughts/"/>
    <id>http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/10/07/odin-project-thoughts/</id>
    <published>2023-10-07T13:20:30.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-10-21T13:00:04.587Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="Pre-amble"><a href="#Pre-amble" class="headerlink" title="Pre-amble"></a>Pre-amble</h1><p>I have already mentioned in the introduction post that I follow <a href="https://www.theodinproject.com/">the Odin Project</a> to study web development. As of now, I am at 92% of the JavaScript course of the <strong>Full Stack Javascript</strong> path. </p><p>Note: after finishing the foundations course I decided to go full stack JS, because I was already familiar with Node.js. For this reason I can’t exactly judge the Ruby on Rails course but I suspect the strong points of the path I chose could be applied to the Ruby on Rails one.</p><p>Yep, I didn’t finish the curriculum yet, you read that right. Nevertheless, I think I am at point where I could provide some <em>food for thought</em> for those thinking if starting TOP is worth it and maybe deciding between courses&#x2F;platforms&#x2F;guides&#x2F;books to study web development.</p><p><em>Again, this is very important: the post below is not a review of the course as a whole but rather a collection of my thoughts about TOP so far.</em></p><h1 id="Material"><a href="#Material" class="headerlink" title="Material"></a>Material</h1><h2 id="General"><a href="#General" class="headerlink" title="General"></a>General</h2><p>The Odin Project does not throw you right into programming in the way most other free resources do, but rather introduce you to some basic concepts that exist in the field. Entry-level material is provided, they make you form your dev environment gradually, never introduce too much concepts as once etc.</p><p>You will never be taught a concept without being provided with ideas how to practice it: from a full-blown project to smaller exercises. You are <em>actively</em> discouraged from skipping practice.</p><p>There is a lesson at the beginning talking about motivation and <a href="https://www.theodinproject.com/lessons/foundations-motivation-and-mindset">mindset</a>. This lesson manages to explain things very coherently, in a way newcomers <em>need</em> to hear, and after finishing it you will be set for studying.</p><h2 id="Vanilla-first"><a href="#Vanilla-first" class="headerlink" title="Vanilla first"></a>Vanilla first</h2><p>TOP is trying not to throw people into frameworks right away, which I see as a very good thing because modern CSS and JS are very powerful and are catching up to their post processors and frameworks.</p><p>By learning vanilla first, a student gets a strong foundation of technology they will use in their job instead of relying wholely on some third-party technology that could pull the rug anytime or become unmaintained.</p><p>This is also good news for the web as a whole, because it teaches people that building simple websites with no 10000 bloated libraries is possible and could even be much faster.</p><h2 id="Additional-resources"><a href="#Additional-resources" class="headerlink" title="Additional resources"></a>Additional resources</h2><p>The course gives you articles and videos as additional resources that are really good and are not actually <em>required</em> to grasp the concept you have been introduced to. So, if you are in a rush, you can skip it completely without losing anything that is important for the basics. </p><p>Though, if you do check it the additional resource, you would understand the concept better or learn some obscure thing that might help you with some non-standard situation or get information on how to avoid it completely.</p><p>Sometimes the additional resources section could feel mundane and because the resources provided might only be a rephrasal of what was already said in the assignment section, but this is not the end of the world and is only true for some rare cases.</p><h1 id="Dev-environment"><a href="#Dev-environment" class="headerlink" title="Dev environment"></a>Dev environment</h1><h2 id="Git"><a href="#Git" class="headerlink" title="Git"></a>Git</h2><p>The course makes you use the <a href="https://git-scm.com/">git</a> version control system <em>early on</em>, which is I think is super important. It’s the small details of TOP that make it so good. You are introduced to git from very early on, which will help you later so much when you will need more advanced features, because by the time you will comfortable with the basics.</p><p>Can we talk about modern day coding without git? No. Working on a bigger project without using git is like going for a long ride on a car without bringing a navigator or at the very least a paper map. You can do it, but <em>why would you</em>?</p><h2 id="GNU-Linux"><a href="#GNU-Linux" class="headerlink" title="GNU&#x2F;Linux"></a>GNU&#x2F;Linux</h2><p>A very important part of the Odin project is that they force you to use GNU&#x2F;Linux for your development work. A UNIX-like system will make your life much easier and won’t introduce any issues because you are studying web development and browsers, surprise, are identical across operating systems.</p><p>Staying on Windows will cause you a lot of time fighting the OS to get something to work, like Node.js, which could be done with a simple command shell script in a minute on a Unix-like system.</p><p>People are used to “Windows” often meaning “easier” and instinctively would want to stay there but in our particular case, switching to a UNIX-like system would actually <em>save</em> time.</p><h1 id="Other"><a href="#Other" class="headerlink" title="Other"></a>Other</h1><h2 id="Feedback"><a href="#Feedback" class="headerlink" title="Feedback"></a>Feedback</h2><p>I loved getting help in the community. You see, you are actually encouraged to do the assignment yourself as much as you can, so even when you do ask for help, you will be <em>directed</em> towards the solution but it won’t be revealed to you. This way, you still develop the thought process that should go in your brain when you solve a problem yourself, but you achieve it faster.</p><p><strong>Feedback</strong> on projects and getting helps when you’re stuck at some part <strong>is a strong side of TOP</strong>. You can share your projects with the community. It is also possible to share your projects through the website, where solutions are displayed based on the amount of stars each projects receives.</p><h2 id="Project-submissions"><a href="#Project-submissions" class="headerlink" title="Project submissions"></a>Project submissions</h2><p><strong>Except when it isn’t</strong>. You see, TOP is volunteer-driven so there is a big chance your project would sink among countless others. On the project solutions section of the website, usually the ones with <em>appealing design</em> get to the top, even if they lack some features or use bad coding practices. I think it would be great if the maintainers chose some reference solutions, so if someone decided to peek at the solution, they would at the very least see a good one that might make them learn a thing or two.</p><p>Also, it would have been nice if TOP pushed newer solutions for others to see, so it’s not impossible to get noticed just because you were late to the party.</p><h2 id="Discord"><a href="#Discord" class="headerlink" title="Discord"></a>Discord</h2><p>Their community is hosted on Discord. It is a reasonable solution considering TOP is free but now that they have started accepting donations, I <em>really</em> hope some of that would go to host a proper forum using software such as Disqus. Discord can be great for getting quick help and general discussion but is not very suitable for making announcements and sharing help.</p><h1 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion"></a>Conclusion</h1><p>It should be noted though that any negative points are fixable because the Odin project is open source so you could contribute to it if you think some parts of it need redaction. The project is in the constant state of improving and updating its resources, which is something that is harder to achieve with books.</p><p>The Odin Project is one of the cases where free is better than a lot of paid alternatives, and if you are not sure where to start your career in webdev, I suggest you go with TOP. It may have some problems here and there but they are insignificant and can be completely dismissed when we consider the free nature of the project. The self-paced learning, diversive types of study material, the coherent structure and practice-oriented studying helped me get out of <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/learnprogramming/comments/qrlx5m/what_exactly_is_tutorial_hell/">tutorial hell</a> and I plan to donate to the maintainers after I land my first job in web development. </p><p>Happy coding!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Reasons why I like the Odin Project.</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="programming" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/programming/"/>
    
    <category term="computers" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/computers/"/>
    
    <category term="the odin project" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/the-odin-project/"/>
    
    <category term="thoughts" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/thoughts/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Art of Paranoia by Shi Zo</title>
    <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/09/10/the-art-of-paranoia/"/>
    <id>http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/09/10/the-art-of-paranoia/</id>
    <published>2023-09-10T19:28:58.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-10-21T12:59:29.604Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are communities on the Internet focused around privacy and security and I, for a long time, participated in them as a member of different chat rooms and forums. Around 6 months ago I got really tired of all of it as they are filled with people with absolutely 0 understanding what a threat model is, giving advice to others that not only wouldn’t help people with anything but defending against <em>mostly</em> imaginary spies but could even hurt their life.</p><p>“Defend against this”, “defend against that”, “always be paranoidal”, “it’s going to help you with security!” Sure, buddy. That’s totally a good reason to cut yourself away from society. </p><p>Lose all your friends because you’re not on any social media anymore for protecting yourself from Mark Zuckerberg reading your thoughts. You wouldn’t want some evil corporation analyzing your <em>public</em> posts, would you? Disable that telemetry in an open source project that lets you see what data is sent — they could be spying on you! It’s not like they just want to improve their software.</p><p>I’m super grateful to Privacy Guides and the New Oil for suggesting reading articles about threat modeling first. Still, that doesn’t save them from people not reading it. </p><p>In my opinion, when paranoidal freaks start sharing their awesome takes, then moderators should step in.</p><p><a href="https://discuss.privacyguides.net/t/keepass/11456/5">You shouldn’t use a popular and actually good password manager software because turns out… it could have security vulnerabilities too! Mindblowing!</a></p><p><a href="https://discuss.privacyguides.net/t/clearnet-email-that-can-be-registered-via-tor/11572">I’m going to use Tor for registering a clearnet email to be “anonymous”</a></p><p><a href="https://discuss.privacyguides.net/t/can-we-not-use-youtube/10416">Should I not use a platform that provides free hosting, automatically creates subtitles, rerenders my videos into different resolutions for free etc. even after I took measures to protect my privacy because Google dares to use data to profit off it</a></p><p>Here is one of the recent ones and my favourite so far:</p><p><a href="https://beehaw.org/comment/1153733">Using YouTube is abused wife mentality</a></p><p><img src="https://i.pinimg.com/originals/dd/11/e2/dd11e28eca8c75556a140ff8e7b230d1--hip-hip-fun-time.jpg" alt="An image of a laptop covered in tin foil. Bottom text reading &quot;Your move, NSA&quot;"></p><p>Rhetoric like the one provided above is all over the place: on Reddit, on Lemmy, on Twitter, on random forums, in Matrix chatrooms, in XMPP chatrooms, in YouTube videos with clickbaitish thumbnails and titles etc.</p><p>Moreover, the tin foil hat society often doesn’t even know that security is, like all matter and thus all other processes and objects, is in the state of constant motion. </p><p>Motion is the way how matter exists: there are no absolute states, there are no invincible armies, there are no unbeatable chess players, there are no humans that don’t do any mistakes etc.</p><p>Offence and defence sides are always thinking of new tactics and strategies to make their opponents’ lives harder. A security vulnerability is going to be patched, a security system is going to be breached.</p><p>They seek absolutely absolute security that they can just apply magically to satisfy their paranoia. That’s why many maintainers and contributors to privacy communities often have to explicitly state that FOSS, for example, does not automatically mean security although it has better potential for being audited.</p><p>Privacy is a human right and it’s great to see people fighting for it so everyone can enjoy it. Projects raising concerns about privacy in the modern world are good because they show that modern tech collects way more data than it is actually needed to operate. </p><p>The problem is that the topic is able to easily trigger paranoia in people and many seem to be ready to introduce hardships into their life to protect themselves from a threat that was never there to begin with.</p><p>Community space of privsec projects can be described as an endless journey of sad cringe for the reasons stated above. That’s why I left it and that’s why I don’t recommend falling into that rabbit hole.</p><p>If what you are reading is making you want to leave society and run away into the woods then maybe you should stop reading it and take your time to process what in the bloody hell did you just read. Just maybe.</p><hr><p>Thank you for taking the time to actually read this. If you have any questions or have any feedback feel free to reach out to me through Fediverse by writing to my Akkoma account that is linked in every post under my nickname and bio.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">When the tin foil hat of self-proclaimed privsec enthusiasts starts damaging the brain.</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="personal" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/personal/"/>
    
    <category term="cybersecurity" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/cybersecurity/"/>
    
    <category term="privacy" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/privacy/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Finished reading about mathematical foundations of cryptology</title>
    <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/09/06/reading-about-cryptology/"/>
    <id>http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/09/06/reading-about-cryptology/</id>
    <published>2023-09-06T16:45:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-10-21T12:58:48.077Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Greetings, my dear and most beloved reader! </p><p>Around a year ago I bought myself a book about cybersecurity. Being a privacybro in the past, I, naturally, wondered how all those fancy encryption algorithms work. That’s why when I learned my uni library has a book on the topic I thought to give reading it a try.</p><p>Today (“Today” stands for “a month ago”, it took me a long time to actually setup my blog and publish this) I am pleased to announce to the world that I have finished reading Chapter 2 of it, named “Mathematical foundations of Cryptology”. I don’t want to lie to you, it was a hard, slow read and I didn’t really grasp <em>all</em> concepts presented in it but now I know what is the logic behind some of the tools I use daily and feel slightly smarter.</p><p>Behind most of cryptology are one-way functions, ones that are easy to compute if you know all parameters but make it hard to “decompute” passed values from the result. Isn’t it impressive how something like discrete logarithm can help you secure communication against another human? Under things that I once categorised as those that border magic lie such simple down-to-Earth concepts. Quality comes from quantity, as Hegel put it over a hundred years ago, and so complexities come from certain amount of simplicities. </p><p>If you’re interested in how things work but don’t want to go into a huge amount of rabbit holes, then consider reading <a href="https://www.techtarget.com/searchsecurity/definition/cryptology">this article</a>, which, in my humble opinion, does a good job explaining things to people who don’t have the time or desire to learn about cryptology in detail and dive deeper into the topic.</p><p>I really want to try implementing the algorithms presented in the book but I also want and have to do a lot of other things, so this is, sadly, not my number 1 priority. Makes me wish there were more than 24 hours in a day so I could pick more past times and hobbies like that.</p><hr><p>Thank you for taking the time to actually read this. If you have any questions or have any feedback feel free to reach out to me through Fediverse by writing to my Akkoma account that is linked in every post under my nickname and bio. Don’t worry, I don’t bite, I promise.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Cryptology is hard but really interesting.</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="computers" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/computers/"/>
    
    <category term="cryptology" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/cryptology/"/>
    
    <category term="cybersecurity" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/cybersecurity/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>First!</title>
    <link href="http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/09/04/first/"/>
    <id>http://verbey.github.io/blog/2023/09/04/first/</id>
    <published>2023-09-03T21:07:04.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-10-21T12:53:31.121Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="Introduce-yourself"><a href="#Introduce-yourself" class="headerlink" title="Introduce yourself"></a>Introduce yourself</h1><p>I’m a self-taught web developer from Eastern Europe organising a little corner for my thoughts on the Internet. My interests are:</p><ul><li><p>Software engineering (Web development in particular). I am currently following the Odin Project, which is focused on Full Stack development, but I plan to move to Back end in the future. My language of choice is JavaScript (Sorry, “Anything other than C is bloat” folks). I chose it because it’s simple, has good looking syntax and is very popular. I also know basics of C&#x2F;C++. </p></li><li><p>GNU&#x2F;Linux. Messing around with my system, feels super fun and helps expand my knowledge of how OSes work.</p></li><li><p>Geeky stuff: anime, tv series, films, videogames. I think I could write reviews for any of these but don’t expect too much (×﹏×)</p></li></ul><h1 id="Why"><a href="#Why" class="headerlink" title="Why?"></a>Why?</h1><p>I love longreads and I always wanted to be able to impress others with my writing as much as some of longreads I read impressed me. I learned not so long ago about the Indie Web and thought giving my own blog a try would be a great idea.</p><h1 id="So-you’re-yet-another-generic-nerd-like-98-of-the-other-people-on-the-Indie-Web"><a href="#So-you’re-yet-another-generic-nerd-like-98-of-the-other-people-on-the-Indie-Web" class="headerlink" title="So you’re yet another generic nerd like 98% of the other people on the Indie Web?"></a>So you’re yet another generic nerd like 98% of the other people on the Indie Web?</h1><p>Yes :)</p><h1 id="Are-you-going-to-be-writing-the-same-stuff-those-nerds-do"><a href="#Are-you-going-to-be-writing-the-same-stuff-those-nerds-do" class="headerlink" title="Are you going to be writing the same stuff those nerds do?"></a>Are you going to be writing the same stuff those nerds do?</h1><p>No. I want to write original content, being a reader of a lot of blogs, I, myself, am tired of constant whining about social media and explanations why should <em>you</em> write and&#x2F;or move to Indie Web.</p><h1 id="Why-does-it-feel-like-a-lot-of-stuff-is-missing"><a href="#Why-does-it-feel-like-a-lot-of-stuff-is-missing" class="headerlink" title="Why does it feel like a lot of stuff is missing?"></a>Why does it feel like a lot of stuff is missing?</h1><p>I am still figuring stuff out so the blog page may seem incomplete. Because it is. As of right now, I didn’t even get my hands out ot figuring out how to access RSS of my blog.</p><h1 id="What-powers-the-blog"><a href="#What-powers-the-blog" class="headerlink" title="What powers the blog?"></a>What powers the blog?</h1><p>The website is generated from Markdown text files using <strong>Hugo</strong> with <strong>Blowfish</strong> theme. It is hosted for free at <strong>Github Pages</strong>.</p><h1 id="Why-Github-Pages-rather-than-Neocities-or-GitLab-Pages-or-Codeberg-Pages"><a href="#Why-Github-Pages-rather-than-Neocities-or-GitLab-Pages-or-Codeberg-Pages" class="headerlink" title="Why Github Pages rather than Neocities or GitLab Pages or Codeberg Pages?"></a>Why Github Pages rather than Neocities or GitLab Pages or Codeberg Pages?</h1><p>Because Github is owned by Microsoft and lets me host my blog for free. Putting load on a corporate server feels good.</p><h1 id="Anything-else-you’ve-got-to-say"><a href="#Anything-else-you’ve-got-to-say" class="headerlink" title="Anything else you’ve got to say?"></a>Anything else you’ve got to say?</h1><p>Thank you for finding this blog and reading up to this moment. Stay safe</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Wake up, babe, a new blog just dropped!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="meta" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/meta/"/>
    
    <category term="personal" scheme="http://verbey.github.io/blog/tags/personal/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
